[MUSIC]
d類效果量
In the previous lecture, we distinguish between two families of effects sizes.
前一講提到兩大類效果量
Going D Family on the one hand and R Family on the other side.
一種稱為d類，另一種稱為r類
In this lecture we'll take a look at
Cohen's D measures of effect sizes.
這一講學習重點是Cohen's d為主的效果量
Standardized mean, differences.
也就是標準化平均值差異
Let's start with a practical example.
從這個實例開始
Do movie ratings differ between websites?
各大電影評論網站的給分有差異嗎？
And if so, how much?
有得話是多少？
Does it actually matter where you go on the internet
這些給分會反應網路上的眾人的評價嗎？
to see how popular a movie is?
Now this is my favorite movie of all time, Fight Club.
拿我最愛的電影「鬥陣俱樂部」來研究吧
I would definitely rate it a ten, myself, but I can understand that taste
我私心的分數是滿分十分，
但是每個人口味不同，想必有不同的評價
differs between people, so there might be some variation.
我私心的分數是滿分十分，
但是每個人口味不同，想必有不同的評價
And there might be a slightly lower average score than ten.
總平均應該會低於十分
Let's take a look at two different websites to see how people have rated
就讓我們看看這部電影在兩個電影網站的大眾評分吧
this movie.
If we go to the Internet Movie Database,
拿IMDb的資料來看
we see that the score is a remarkably low 8.9, okay.
平均得分是讓我有點心碎的8.9
But if you visit Rotten Tomatoes,
再看爛蕃茄的資料
we see that the score that people gave Fight Club is actually 7.3 out of 10.
網路鄉民給的評價是滿分10分的7.3分
This is actually a big difference if you look at it like this but
兩大網站的評分有很大的差異
we need to quantify this difference to be sure.
因此需要仔細衡量兩者之間的差異
Is this really meaningful or not?
是不是真的反映兩個網站口味不同？
So let's calculate the standardized mean difference to find out.
所以我們要計算兩者的標準化平均值差異
Now we have the two mean values.
現在把兩大網站的平均評分放在一起
On the one hand, the Internet Movie
Database, where the evaluation for
8.9是IMDb的評分，7.3是爛蕃茄的評分
Fight Club is an 8.9, and on Rotten
Tomatoes the average evaluation is a 7.3.
8.9是IMDb的評分，7.3是爛蕃茄的評分
Now conceptually, the standardized mean difference
在統計學裡，標準化平均值差異是
is the difference in means divided by the standard deviation.
平均值的差異除以標準差
So here we have two means, and we can subtract the one from the other
所以首先把一個平均值減去另一個平均值
to get the mean difference, but we also
need to know the standard deviation.
不過我們還需要知道標準差
Now luckily, I happen to know that if you look at all movie evaluations that
還好我得知網站的計算方式和原始資料
are being done, the standard deviation is, more or less, 1.4 on these scales.
所以標準差不多不少是1.4
If you have 10 point scale then the standard deviation you can expect if
也就是以10點量表讓網路鄉民評分
people evaluate movies 1.4.
個別差異大約是1.4
So we can have the mean difference and
有了平均值差異和標準差，就能計算效果量
divide it by the standard deviation to calculate the effect size.
In this case,
計算之後
the Cohen's d is a 1.14 which as we'll see later is a very big effect.
得到Cohen's d是1.4
稍後會告訴你這是相當大的效果量
So it really matters which website you go to,
所以IMDb和爛蕃茄給鬥陣俱樂部的評價是很不一樣的
if you want to know whether people like a movie.
A Cohen's d ranges from 0, no effect, to infinity.
Cohen's d的數值可以是0到無限大
When there's no difference between two groups, the mean difference is 0,
沒有差異的話，不論標準差多少，平均值差異都是0
and you can divide it by any
standard deviation you want.
沒有差異的話，不論標準差多少，平均值差異都是0
The effect size will remain zero.
效果量也會是0
If the difference is really really huge
then the effect size just goes up and up.
如果效果確實巨大，效果量的數值隨差異增加
Now let's visualize different effect sizes.
讓我們用視覺化方法了解效果量大小的意義
If you don't have any idea of how to interpret an effect size,
有一套評價標準讓你可以推測效果量是大是小
then there are useful benchmarks you can use.
And in this effect size you can use the benchmarks of 0.2 for small effects.
0.2是小效果量的下限
0.5 for medium effect, and 0.8 for a large effect.
過了0.5就算中效果量
超過0.8就是大效果量
In this graph, we see the visualization for an effect size of 0.2.
這張圖展示效果量0.2的分配差異
So, clearly there's the difference, people in the one group are slightly more likely
如果把兩個分配當成兩個網站的評分次數分佈
to have a higher score or evaluate a movie a little bit better than the other group
右邊這一群是比左邊的評分稍高
but you can also see that there's quite a lot of overlap.
不過兩者的重疊比例還是很高
One individual from one group is very likely
比較高分的這一群
even though they're from this group that on average has a higher evaluation for
即使給的分數接近這一群的平均值
a movie to like the movie less than someone from the other group.
也是比另一群多數人的評分稍低
If we look at the slightly bigger effects size Cohen's d: 0.5
如果效果量增加到0.5
we can see the difference is bigger.
兩個分配的差異也變大
There still quite some overlap.
但還是有很高的重疊比例
And Cohen's d is 0.8 is considered a large meaningful effect.
現在增加到剛剛說的大效果量下限0.8
This is really a big effect size and not many effects in psychology for
如此的效果量數值很少出現在心理學文獻之中
example are as big as this.
And even in this situation there's still quite a lot of overlap.
這張圖裡的兩群重疊比例還是很高
Sometimes you might be tempted to think that if there is a significant result,
概念清楚的研究者會想就算是統計顯著
significant effect.
是否有實質的差異
Then everybody in one group should score higher than everybody in the other group.
右邊這一群所有人的給分應該比左邊所有人高
But this distributions clearly show that this is not the case.
但是從分配來看似乎不是如此
Even when we have a big effect, groups overlap quite a bit.
就算是有大效果量，還是有重疊的部分
Now using this benchmarks, 'large',
'medium', or 'small' to interpret
剛剛說的小中大效果量判斷標準其實是最後的依據
the size of your effect Should be only be used as a last resort.
They're useful if you don't have anything else to go on but,
是你沒有其他可參考的資訊時才要用
it's typically already better to compare the effect size that you found to
一般來說從文獻中找類似研究的效果量更可靠
other related effects in the literature.
You might be able to make a statement such as well compare to
由此比較得到的結論會更站得住腳
this type of intervention.
This intervention has a smaller or bigger effect size.
文獻比較能顯示效果量的相對大小
And this is better than just using these benchmarks.
比單純的統計學判斷標準更好
Sometimes this is not possible and these benchmarks are all you have to go on.
當然沒有文獻可供比較時，還是只能依賴判斷標準。
So interpreting them in the minimum case should require these benchmarks but
請記得這些判斷標準是不得已時才使用
hopefully you can interpret the effect size and
儘可能透過收集文獻數據推測效果量大小的意義
slightly more meaningful way by relating them to effects in the literature.
So conceptually Cohen's d is the difference divided by the standard
Cohen's d的計算概念是差異值除以標準差
deviation but there are a lot of small variations of Cohen's d
但是標準差的計算取決於獲得資料的研究設計
depending on the design that you use, for example within subject design or
between subject design.
像是受試者內或受試者間設計
There's the Cohen's d for
有的計算方式是用於已知母群參數的
the population if you would know the true value and there's the Cohen's d for
the sample if you calculate the effect size based on the sup group.
還有計算方式是用於已知樣本估計值的
And all these small variations might become a little bit complex but
這些計算公式的差別有些小複雜
they're important to keep in mind.
但要使用的話必須先分清楚
They differ a little bit and
如果你想仔細了解各種公式的差別
可以看看我的這篇論文
if you want to take a look at this you can look at an article I wrote about this.
如果你想仔細了解各種公式的差別
可以看看我的這篇論文
I don't want to advertise my own work but
我不是故意要打廣告
people apparently seem to find this specific article useful.
而是這篇論文剛好解決這方面的需要
And in this article, I give you all the different formulas for
我在這篇論文列出所有版本的公式及適用條件
these slightly different versions of effect sizes.
It's important to keep in mind which effect size you should use,
切記要了解那個公式符合你的研究需求
especially when you perform power calculations.
特別是計算統計檢定力時
So this is a screen shot of g power which you can use to perform a power analysis.
像是G Power裡的效果量欄位裡要填的數值
And in this case, we're performing a power analysis for a dependent test.
這個例子是相依樣本檢定的檢定力分析
There are two groups, but they are dependent.
兩組平均值出自有關聯性的樣本
In this case, G Power asks you to fill in Cohen's dz.
需要在G Power輸入Cohen's dz
So this is one specific way to calculate the standardized mean difference.
為此需要用特別方法計算標準化平均值差異
If you use a different way to calculate the standardized effect size you might get
如果你不是用正確方法計算標準化效果量
an incorrect sample size estimate based on the power analysis.
檢定力分析可能會得到錯誤的樣本數估計值
So keep this in mind.
切記公式的不同
We have a difference between unbiased and biased effect size estimates.
有時候需要效果量的不偏誤估計值
It turns out that if you just calculate Cohen's d.
這時只算Cohen's d是不夠的
It slightly over estimates the true effect size.
因為Choen's d會高估真實效果
Especially when you have small sample sizes,
尤其是樣本數不大的數據
this can be a little bit of a problem.
可能會造成一些問題
Since you're most likely to use computer software to calculate
即然現在幾乎都是用電腦程式計算效果量
the effects size anyway.
It makes sense to always calculate the unbiased version
應該儘可能去計算平均值差異的不偏估計值
of the d family effect sizes.
In this case, it's called Hedges' g.
就像Hedges' g
You can see that the g is just Cohen's d multiplied by a small correction.
從公式可看出g等於Cohen's d乘以校正係數
And this correction is only dependent up on the sample size.
這項校正係數由樣本數決定
The larger the sample there's all else no correction.
樣本數越大，校正幅度越小
But if you have a very small sample the difference can be enough to be meaningful.
若是你的資料是小樣本，這樣的校正就有意義
You can also calculate effect sizes from the population literature.
也可以使用文獻中的數值計算效果量
It's not always the case that researchers write down what the effect size is,
多數論文不見得會在結果的段落中真接呈現效果量
that they have calculated this effect size and reported it in the results section.
If this is not the case, that's fine.
如果沒有也不必抱怨
In many cases there's enough information in the results section to
多數論文已呈現讀者可以自行計算效果量的資訊
calculate the effect size yourself.
For example, Cohen's d can be directly calculated from
像是Cohen's d能用t值與樣本數計算
the t value in the t-test and the sample size.
Cohen's d for a within and a between design differ.
受試者內與受試者間的Cohen's d是不一樣的
You might have the same mean difference, but
即使平均值差異相同
observations in a within design are correlated.
受試者內的組間觀察值是相關的
This implies that if the correlation is really high,
從公式可看出若觀察值關聯性夠強
the effect size that's calculated based on the observation can be higher in a within
受試者內設計的效果量會高於
受試者間設計的效果量
design than in a between design, depending on the strength of the correlation.
受試者內設計的效果量會高於
受試者間設計的效果量
The difference in the Cohen's d in a within design and
因為兩者間的差異是由這張投影片結尾的係數
所決定
a between design is the square root of 2(1- r).
因為兩者間的差異是由這張投影片結尾的係數
所決定
This implies that whenever the correlation between dependent measures is
相依樣本觀察值的相關係數大於0.5時
larger than 0.5, this difference vector is higher than 1,
差異係數會大於1
which means the d in a within design would be higher.
使得受試者內設計的效果量提高
This also means, that the power in such a design is higher.
也代表受試者內設計有較高的檢定力
In many psychological task, correlations between dependent measures are very high.
許多心理學實驗有很高的相依樣本關聯性
So, very strong correlation which means that very often
相關係數越高表示這種作業採用受試者內設計
within designs will be more powerful than between designs.
會比受試者間設計有更高的檢定力
We already mentioned that it's important to report and interpret effect sizes.
這一講再次說明報告與解讀效果量的重要性
You can interpret effect sizes in relation to small, medium, and large benchmarks.
我們有判斷標準判別小中大效果量
But it's always better to try to interpret these effect sizes in relation to effects
不過根據文獻報告推論效果量之間的差異是最好的
in the literature.
Whenever you use these effects or empower analysis for
不論是不是在檢定力分析使用效果量
example when you report them in your results make sure that you realize their
必須先了解是根據什麼研究設計
small differences within the d family, depending on the design that you've used.
報告與解釋平均值的標準差異
[MUSIC]
影片結束